<Class id="npm" public="true">
	<metadata>
		<name>npm</name>
		<short-description>Provides direct access to npm packages</short-description>
		<discussion>
		<![CDATA[
			<p>
				The <code>npm</code> object provides access to all <a href="https://www.npmjs.com">npm</a> packages.<br>
				Both <a href="https://nodejs.org/api/esm.html#modules-ecmascript-modules">ESM</a> and <a href="https://nodejs.org/api/modules.html#modules-commonjs-modules">CommonJS</a> exports are supported.
			</p>
			<p>
				You do <em>not</em> need to import or install the packages you use in any way; Tasklemon will automatically download and inject any package you access.
			</p>
		]]>
		</discussion>
		<related>
		<![CDATA[
			To fetch arbitrary data from the Internet, use <df-class>net</df-class>.
		]]>
		</related>
	</metadata>
	<details>
		<detail name="Using ESM packages" id="using-esm-packages">
			<discussion>
			<![CDATA[
				<p>
					Modern npm packages usually expose their functionality as ESM modules.
				</p>
				
				<p>	
					To use such a package, access it through the <code>npm</code> global:
					<ul>
						<li>
							The package's <strong>default export</strong> is exposed directly.<br>
							For instance, <code>npm.chalk</code> returns the default export of the <code>chalk</code> package.
						</li>
						<li>
							The package's <strong>named exports</strong> are exposed as properties.<br>
							For instance, <code>npm.telegram.TelegramClient</code> returns the <code>TelegramClient</code> export of the <code>telegram</code> package.
						</li>
					</ul>
				</p>
			
				<df-sample name="Use the boxen package's default export">
cli.tell(npm.boxen(" Hello! "));
/*            ┌────────┐
   Displays:  │ Hello! │
              └────────┘ */
				</df-sample>
			
				<df-sample name="Use the “length” named export of the stringz package">
cli.tell(npm.stringz.length("👩🏿‍💻 Contributing"));
// Displays “14”
				</df-sample>
				
				<p>
					In rare cases, there can be collisions between injected named exports, and default export properties. See <df-link target="#accessing-shadowed-default-export-properties">Accessing shadowed default export properties</df-link> for a solution.
				</p>
			]]>
			</discussion>
		</detail>
		<detail name="Using CommonJS packages" id="using-commonjs-packages">
			<discussion>
			<![CDATA[
				<p>
					Many other packages, including older ones, expose their functionality as CommonJS modules.
				</p>
				
				<p>
					You can use these packages in the same way as ESM-based packages, by accessing them directly on the <code>npm</code> global.
				</p>
			
				<df-sample name="Use the dedupe package">
const friendNames = await cli.ask('What are your friends called?', Array);
const uniqueFriendNames = npm.dedupe(friendNames);

cli.tell('Total count of unique friend names: ' + uniqueFriendNames.length);
				</df-sample>
				
				<p>
					If a package has conflicting ESM and CommonJS exports, Tasklemon will return the ESM export.
				</p>
			]]>
			</discussion>
		</detail>
		<detail name="Requiring specific versions" id="specifying-versions">
			<discussion>
			<![CDATA[
				<p>
					If your script needs a specific version of a package, you can add a package version directive at the top of your script.<br>
					Add the directive below the shebang, if any, and above the script's code.
				</p>
			
				<df-sample name="Specify which version of username to use">
// tl:require: username@5.0.0

cli.tell('Hello, ' + await npm.username() + '!');
				</df-sample>
				
				<p>
					It's a good idea to do this, to ensure your script's behavior stays the same over time, even after new versions of the packages are released.
					To have Tasklemon automatically add a <code>tl:require</code> directive for all the packages used by your script, setting them to their latest available version, you can use the <code>--pin-pkg</code> command-line action.<br>
				</p>
				
				<df-sample name="Automatically add version directives to a script">
$ lemon --pin-pkg script.js
				</df-sample>
			]]>
			</discussion>
		</detail>
		<detail name="Using packages named with special characters" id="using-packages-named-with-special-characters">
			<discussion>
			<![CDATA[
				<p>
					To access a package with special characters in its name, such as a scoped package, use bracket notation.
				</p>
				
				<df-sample name="Use the UUID package from Allthings">
const uuid = npm['@allthings/uuid'];
cli.tell('New unique identifier: ' + uuid());
				</df-sample>
			]]>
			</discussion>
		</detail>
		<detail name="Requiring nested files" id="requiring-sub-files">
			<discussion>
			<![CDATA[
				<p>
					If your script needs to use a specific sub-file of a package, rather than the package's main file, you can specify the file's path, separated by a colon.
				</p>
				
				<df-sample name="Use the v4 mode of the uuid package">
const uuid = npm['uuid:v4'];
cli.tell('New unique identifier: ' + uuid());
				</df-sample>
			]]>
			</discussion>
		</detail>
		<detail name="Accessing shadowed default export properties" id="accessing-shadowed-default-export-properties">
			<discussion>
			<![CDATA[
				<p>
					Most of the time, when using ESM packages, there is no collision between named exports, and properties on the default export.<br>
					However, if you do need to access a property that's been shadowed, you can do so through the raw default export, accessible as the <code>unmodifiedDefaultExport</code> property.
				</p>
				<p>
					For example, consider a package named <code>contrivedExample</code>. Its default export has an <code>ambiguousLabel</code> property; and one of its named exports happens to be named <code>ambiguousLabel</code> as well. In this situation:
					<ul>
						<li>
							<code>npm.contrivedExample.ambiguousLabel</code> returns the <code>ambiguousLabel</code> named export.
						</li>
						<li>
							<code>npm.contrivedExample.unmodifiedDefaultExport.ambiguousLabel</code> returns the <code>ambiguousLabel</code> property of the default export.
						</li>
					</ul>
				</p>
			]]>
			</discussion>
		</detail>
		<detail name="Managing the cache" id="managing-the-cache">
			<discussion>
			<![CDATA[
				<p>
					In order to ensure a script can execute offline, and without any download delays, you can ask Tasklemon to preload all of the script's required packages. These include packages you implicitely require, not just the packages pinned by version directives.<br>
					This has no purpose for a script that's been run at least once, since Tasklemon will already have downloaded its packages.
				</p>
				
				<df-sample name="Preload the packages used by a script">
$ lemon --preload-pkg script.js
				</df-sample>
				
				<p>
					Tasklemon's package cache is generally very resilient, and can recover from most download and installation issues. If something seems broken, however, you can try emptying the package cache.
				</p>
				
				<df-sample name="Empty the package cache">
$ lemon --clear-pkg-cache
				</df-sample>
			]]>
			</discussion>
		</detail>
	</details>
</Class>
